<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="style.css"?>
<?xml-model href="./schema/dahprojects.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title xml:lang="en">Digital art history project directory</title>
        <title xml:lang="fr">Répertoire de projets en histoire de l’art numérique</title>
        <editor>
          <persName>
            <forename>Emmanuel</forename>
            <surname>Château-Dutier</surname>
          </persName>
          <orgName>Université de Montréal</orgName>
        </editor>
        <editor>
          <persName>
            <forename>Léa</forename>
            <surname>Maronet</surname>
          </persName>
          <orgName>Université de Montréal</orgName>
        </editor>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>/img/lab</publisher>
        <date from="2015-12">Depuis décembre 2015</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>Natively digital</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <p>L’encodage diverge de la TEI, la documentation du schema avec ODD est en cours.</p>
    </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <listBibl>
        <head>Éditions critiques</head>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Leonardo da Vinci &amp; his treatise on painting</title>
            <principal>
              <persName>
                <forename>Francesca</forename>
                <surname>Fiorani</surname>
              </persName>
            </principal>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>The Institute for Advanced Technology in the Humanities, University of
              Virginia</publisher>
            <date when="2012">2012</date>
            <idno>http://www.treatiseonpainting.org</idno>
          </publicationStmt>
          <notesStmt>
            <note>
              <p>Leonardo da Vinci and His Treatise on Painting is a digital archive dedicated to
                the Treatise on Painting, the pivotal text for disseminating Leonardo's art theory
                in Renaissance and Baroque Europe. Rather than focusing on Leonardo's original
                manuscripts, which remained largely unavailable until the early nineteenth century,
                the digital archive focuses on the Treatise on Painting, the only text by Leonardo
                that circulated widely in Renaissance and Baroque Europe.</p>
              <p>In collaboration with institutional partners and private collectors from across the
                globe, the digital archive gathers for the first time, in a single place, critical
                resource materials on the legacy and reception of Leonardo's art theory. </p></note>
          </notesStmt>
        </biblFull>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">History of the Accadmeia di San Luca, c. 1590-1635</title>
            <title type="sub">Documents form the Archivio di Stato di Roma</title>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>National Gallery of Art</publisher>
            <publisher>Center for Advanced Study in the Visual Arts</publisher>
            <idno>http://www.nga.gov/casva/accademia/</idno>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Vincent Van Gogh, The Letters</title>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Van Gogh Museum</authority>
            <publisher>Huygens ING</publisher>
            <date when="2009">2009</date>
            <idno>http://vangoghletters.org/vg/</idno>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Pietro Mellini’s Inventory in Verse 1681</title>
            <title type="sub">A Digital Facsimile with Translation and Commentary</title>
            <principal>
              <persName>
                <forename>Murtha</forename>
                <surname>Baca</surname>
              </persName>
              <persName>
                <forename>Nuria</forename>
                <surname>Rodríguez Ortega</surname>
              </persName>
            </principal>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Getty</publisher>
            <idno>http://www.getty.edu/research/mellini/</idno>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Élie-Honoré Montagny’s Recueil d'Antiquités</title>
            <title type="sub">A Digital Critical Edition</title>
            <principal>
              <!-- direction générale du projet -->
              <persName>
                <forename>Martine</forename>
                <surname>Denoyelle</surname>
              </persName>
              <orgName>Institut national d’histoire de l’art (INHA)</orgName>
            </principal>
            <respStmt>
              <resp>éditeur scientifique, direction du projet</resp>
              <persName>
                <forename>Delphine</forename>
                <surname>Burlot</surname>
              </persName>
              <orgName>Institut national d’histoire de l’art (INHA)</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
              <resp>directrice du département d’histoire de l’art numérique</resp>
              <persName>
                <forename>Murtha</forename>
                <surname>Baca</surname>
              </persName>
              <orgName>Getty Research Institute (GRI)</orgName>
            </respStmt>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Institut national d’histoire de l’art (INHA)</publisher>
            <date when="2015-09">septembre 2015</date>
            <idno>http://digitalmontagny.inha.fr</idno>
          </publicationStmt>
          <notesStmt>
            <note>
              <p>Date de mise en ligne septembre 2015</p>
              <p>Conçu et réalisé en étroite collaboration par l’Institut national d’histoire de
                l’art et le Getty Research Institute, ce site porte sur le Recueil d’Antiquités
                d’Élie-Honoré Montagny, un remarquable album de dessins du début du XIXe siècle,
                conservé dans les Special Collections du Getty Research Institute (2004.M.12), qui
                documente des objets antiques présents à Naples et à Rome à cette époque.</p>
              <p>Publication réalisée avec Drupal. Format d’export XML avec des éléments encodés
                !</p>
            </note>
          </notesStmt>
        </biblFull>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">The History of the Accademia di San Luca, c. 1590-1635</title>
            <title type="sub">Documents from the Archivio di Stato di Roma</title>
            <principal>
              <persName>
                <forename>Peter</forename>
                <surname>Lukehart</surname>
              </persName>
            </principal>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Center for Advanced Study in the Visual Arts, National Gallery of
              Art</publisher>
            <idno>http://www.nga.gov/content/accademia/en/intro.html</idno>
            <date from="2005" to="2015">2005 à 2015</date>
          </publicationStmt>
          <notesStmt>
            <note>
              <p>Welcome to The History of the Accademia di San Luca, c. 1590–1635: Documents from
                the Archivio di Stato di Roma. This site makes available archival documents and
                other research materials concerning one of the first artists’ academies in Europe.
                These resources document the breadth of the Accademia’s activities, drawing from the
                proceedings of meetings, financial and legal transactions, property rentals, and
                other records. New documents and research materials are added to the site
                periodically, all cross-referenced to people connected with the academy’s
                institutional and professional concerns and the places where they interacted.</p>
              <p>First launched in 2010, the site was initially created using Extensible Markup
                Language (XML) within the parameters of the Text Encoding Initiative (TEI) [1]. In
                2014 the site was migrated to the platform used by the National Gallery of Art
                website to ensure its long-term sustainability and extensibility. Search parameters
                initially developed in 2010 were enhanced after the 2014 site migration. The site’s
                original documents and features have been re-edited and updated to correct errors
                and inconsistencies as well as to incorporate new information.</p>
              <p>The current site is driven by the National Gallery of Art's content management and
                site design platform. High resolution images are managed through the Java Script
                Object Notation (JSON) file format, compatible with Application Programming
                Interface (API) viewing applications using the International Image Interoperability
                Framework (IIIF), specifically Mirador and IIPMooViewer. The site is built on Hyper
                Text Markup Language (HTML) with Cascading Style Sheets (CSS) and JavaScript
                Framework (jQuery).</p>
            </note>
          </notesStmt>
        </biblFull>

        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Manart</title>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher/>
            <pubPlace>France</pubPlace>
            <idno>http://www.basemanart.com</idno>
          </publicationStmt>
          <notesStmt>
            <note>
              <p>Manart est un projet construit autour de la base de données du même nom sur les
                MANifestes ARTistiques. Elle contient des manifestes produits au XX<hi
                  rend="superscript">e</hi> siècle dans toutes les disciplines artistiques et dans
                toutes les sphères géographiques. La richesse d’information rassemblée pour chaque
                manifeste autorise des questionnements qui contribuent à élargir et à nuancer les
                perspectives d’analyse du manifeste comme genre. Reposant sur le principe
                d’alimentation collaborative, Manart s’offre comme une plateforme de recherche
                ouverte et internationale autour du phénomène manifestaire et, plus largement, en
                histoire et sociologie de l’art.</p>
            </note>
          </notesStmt>
        </biblFull>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Bibliographie de critiques d’art francophones</title>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Université Panthéon-Sorbonne</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Paris (France)</pubPlace>
            <idno>http://critiquesdart.univ-paris1.fr</idno>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Szeemann Digital Seminar</title>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Getty Researche Institute</publisher>
            <date from="2017-09">septembre 2017</date>
            <idno>https://www.getty.edu/research/scholars/digital_art_history/szeemann_digital_seminar/</idno>
          </publicationStmt>
          <notesStmt>
            <note>
              <p>The seminar used digital technologies (Getty Scholars' Workspace v 1.1, the Digital
                Archive Navigation Application, and a customized image viewer from the IIIF
                community) to enable collaboration among three graduate seminars at UCLA, the
                University of Chicago, and the Academy of Fine Arts, Leipzig, all focused on the
                work of seminal curator Harald Szeemann, whose extraordinary archive is housed at
                the Research Institute. </p>
              <p>The students research newly digitized materials from the Harald Szeemann Archive
                and use collaborative tools developed by the Research Institute, including Getty
                Scholars' Workspace™, to explore the relationships between Szeemann's collecting and
                research interests and to present findings to their peers. Results and lessons
                learned from the project will be published online following the conclusion of the
                seminar.</p>
            </note>
          </notesStmt>
        </biblFull>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Adam Grand Tour Online</title>
            <title type="sub">Robert &amp; James Adam’s Grand Tour letters and writings
              1754–63</title>
            <funder>Paul Mellon Centre for Studies in British Art</funder>
            <sponsor>UCL’s Bartlett School of Architecture</sponsor>
            <sponsor>University of Buckingham’s Department of History and History of Art</sponsor>
            <editor>
              <persName>
                <forename>Adriano</forename>
                <surname>Aymonino</surname>
              </persName>
            </editor>
            <editor>
              <persName>
                <forename>Colin</forename>
                <surname>Thom</surname>
              </persName>
            </editor>
            <respStmt>
              <resp>technical director</resp>
              <persName>
                <forename>Giles</forename>
                <surname>Bergel</surname>
              </persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
              <resp>project’s transcriber</resp>
              <persName>
                <forename>Harriet</forename>
                <surname>Richardson</surname>
              </persName>
            </respStmt>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher ref="https://www.soane.org">Sir John Soane’s Museum</publisher>
            <date from="2020" to="2022">2020-2022</date>
          </publicationStmt>
          <notesStmt>
            <note>
              <p>Welcome to the website of Robert &amp; James Adam’s Grand Tour letters and writings
                1754–63. The aim of this project is to present an online critical edition of all the
                known Adam brothers’ Grand Tour letters and writings as a freely available,
                open-access, fully searchable database. This will enable readers to view the letters
                in their original form alongside new and accurate transcriptions, with contextual
                scholarly annotations. </p>
            </note>
            <note type="licence">CC BY-NC-SA</note>
          </notesStmt>
        </biblFull>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">eMunch</title>
            <title type="sub">Edvard Munchs Tekster Digitalt Arkiv</title>
            <editor>
              <forename>Hilde</forename>
              <surname>Bøe</surname>
            </editor>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Munchmuseet</publisher>
            <date from="2011" to="2016">2011-2016</date>
            <idno>https://www.emunch.no</idno>
          </publicationStmt>
          <notesStmt>
            <note><p>Digitalisering Museets prosjektgruppe arbeider med digitalisering av
                korrespondansen til Edvard Munch samt med ferdigstilling av Munchs egne tekster.
                Materialet korrekturleses og kodes før det publiseres her. Alle registrerte
                avsendere (med lister over brevene de sendte til Munch) og omtalte personer og
                institusjoner blir etter hvert tilgjengelig her i det digitale arkivet.</p></note>
          </notesStmt>
        </biblFull>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>BoschDoc</title>
            <funder>Radboud University Nijmegen</funder>
            <funder>City Archives of ’s-Hertogenbosch</funder>
            <funder>Huygens ING</funder>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher ref="https://www.huygens.knaw.nl">Huygens ING</publisher>
            <date from="2016">2016</date>
            <idno>https://boschdoc.huygens.knaw.nl</idno>
          </publicationStmt>
          <notesStmt>
            <note><p>BoschDoc is an online database containing source material on the
                ’s-Hertogenbosch painter Hieronymus Bosch. Not only the sources in which he himself
                is mentioned are included, but also sources giving information about his immediate
                surroundings, members of his family, patrons and works. These are chiefly
                handwritten documents, but also a number of early printed works, dating from before
                1800 are included in BoschDoc.</p><p>BoschDoc is part of the Bosch Research and
                Conservation Project and has been carried out in the framework of the 500th
                anniversary of the death of Hieronymus Bosch (c. 1450 – 1516). The project has been
                made possible by the Radboud University Nijmegen, the City Archives of
                ’s-Hertogenbosch and the Huygens ING.</p><p>The content of BoschDoc is largely based
                on references in other publications. These references have been traced, expanded and
                if necessary updated and/or corrected. The publications containing the references
                are credited under the tab “Comments &amp; References”.</p></note>
          </notesStmt>
        </biblFull>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Der Sturm</title>
            <title>Digitale Quellenedition zur Geschichte der internationalen Avantgarde</title>
            <editor>
              <forename>Marjam</forename>
              <surname>Trautmann</surname>
            </editor>
            <editor>
              <forename>Torsten</forename>
              <surname>Schrade</surname>
            </editor>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Akademie der Wissenschaften und der Literatur</publisher>
            <date from="2018">2018</date>
            <idno>https://sturm-edition.de</idno>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>The Thorvaldsens Museum archives</title>
            <editor>
              <forename>Ernst Jonas</forename>
              <surname>Bencard</surname>
            </editor>
            <editor>
              <forename>Karen Benedicte</forename>
              <surname>Busk-Jepsen</surname>
            </editor>
            <editor>
              <forename>Nanna</forename>
              <surname>Kronberg Frederiksen</surname>
            </editor>
            <editor>
              <forename>Kira</forename>
              <surname>Kofoed</surname>
            </editor>
            <editor>
              <forename>Lejla</forename>
              <surname>Mrgan</surname>
            </editor>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Thorvaldsens Museum</publisher>
            <date from="2013" to="2020">2013-2020</date>
            <idno>https://arkivet.thorvaldsensmuseum.dk</idno>
          </publicationStmt>
          <notesStmt>
            <note>
              <p>This site is a research and documentation centre on Bertel Thorvaldsen and his art.
                Published here you will find comprehensive written source material on the sculptor
                and his art.</p>
              <p>The bulk of the material is transcripts of all written primary sources left by
                Thorvaldsen, and kept today at his museum. More than half of the documents are
                letters to, from and about the sculptor. They were uncovered in Rome just after the
                death of Thorvaldsen; see History of the Archives for more on this.</p>
            </note>
          </notesStmt>
        </biblFull>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Brieven en Correspondenten rond 1900</title>
            <editor>
              <forename>Annemarie</forename>
              <surname>Kets</surname>
            </editor>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Huygens Instituut voor Nederlandse Geschiedenis</publisher>
            <date when="2016">2016</date>
            <idno>https://brieven-correspondenten-1900.huygens.knaw.nl</idno>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">The Mondrian Papers</title>
            <title type="sub">The complete letters and theoretical writings of Piet Mondrian</title>
            <editor>
              <persName>
                <forename>Wietse</forename>
                <surname>Coppes</surname>
              </persName>
            </editor>
            <editor>
              <persName>
                <forename>Leo</forename>
                <surname>Jansen</surname>
              </persName>
            </editor>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Netherlands Institute for Art History (RKD)</publisher>
            <publisher>the Huygens Institute for Dutch History (KNAW)</publisher>
            <date from="2012" to="2027">2012-2027</date>
            <idno>https://mondrianpapers.org</idno>
          </publicationStmt>
          <noteStmt>
            <note xml:lang="en">
              <p>The Mondrian Papers is an academic online edition of the entire correspondence and
                theoretical writings of the Dutch artist Piet Mondrian (1872-1944). The edition will
                be fully annotated and illustrated. All relevant secondary sources (personal
                documents, studio and portrait photos, amongst others) are also included in the
                edition.</p>
              <p>The Mondrian Papers is a work in progress and will be published in parts. This site
                will keep you updated on the developments whilst also offering information on the
                background of the Mondrian Edition Project, of which The Mondrian Papers is the
                result.</p>
            </note>
          </noteStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </listBibl>
      <listBibl>
        <head>Projets en histoire de l'art numérique</head>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Amiens Cathedral Project</title>
            <principal>
              <persName>
                <forename>Stephen</forename>
                <surname>Murray</surname>
              </persName>
            </principal>
            <funder>National Endowment for the Humanities</funder>
            <funder>Samuel H. Kress Foundation</funder>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Media Center for Art History</authority>
            <publisher>Columbia University</publisher>
            <pubPlace>United States of America</pubPlace>
            <date when="1996">1996</date>
            <idno>http://learn.columbia.edu/Mcahweb/index-frame.html</idno>
          </publicationStmt>
          <notesStmt>
            <note type="abstract" xml:lang="fr">
              <p>Dirigé par Stephen Murray, professeur d’histoire de l’art et d’archéologie à
                l’université de Columbia, le <title>Amiens project</title> consiste en une archive
                de divers matériaux multimédias pour rendre compte de l’espace authentique de la
                cathédrale.</p>
              <p>Plusieurs sections du site proposent des archives iconographiques de l’intérieur et
                de l’extérieur de l’édifice accompagnées d’une riche documentation textuelle. Il
                présente rassemble ainsi des clichés photographiques du bâtiment, des
                reconstitutions virtuelles, diverses pièces de documentation graphique ainsi que des
                relevés architecturaux.</p>
              <p>Une rubrique du site présente notamment une animation de treize minutes conçue en
                images 3D conçue pour un usage pédagogique. Outre ce film, une section intitulée
                  <ref target="http://learn.columbia.edu/1k_years/">A Thousand Years of Chruch
                  Architecture</ref> présente des diagrammes en flash sur l’évolution des formes
                architecturales religieuses à l’époque médiévale. Le programme iconographique est
                quant à lui présenté au moyen d’animations interactives avec des références aux
                sources religieuses textuelles. Enfin, une page du site accueillait des discussions
                avec les utilisateurs au moyen du service HTML Gear Discussion Board offert par
                Lycos jusqu’en avril 2012.</p>
              <p>Le projet avait été conçu comme le prototype de ce que pourrait régulièrement
                produire, à cette époque, le nouveau <orgName>Media Center for the Arts</orgName> en
                tant que suppléments au programme d’art et d’humanités offert dans l’université.</p>
            </note>
            <note type="projectBib">
              <biblStruct>
                <analytic>
                  <title type="a">The Amiens Project</title>
                  <author>
                    <persName>
                      <forename>Brett</forename>
                      <surname>Forman</surname>
                    </persName>
                  </author>
                </analytic>
                <monogr>
                  <title type="j">Columbia Magazine</title>
                  <imprint>
                    <date when="1996">1996</date>
                    <biblScope unit="issue">Summer 1996</biblScope>
                  </imprint>
                </monogr>
                <ref type="url"
                  >http://www.columbia.edu/cu/record/archives/vol22/vol22_iss1/Amiens_Proj.html</ref>
              </biblStruct>
              <biblStruct>
                <analytic>
                  <title type="a">Amiens, a Medieval City, Recreated in a Columbia
                    Laboratory</title>
                </analytic>
                <monogr>
                  <title type="j">Columbia University Record</title>
                  <imprint>
                    <date when="1995-11-17">17 novembre 1995</date>
                    <biblScope unit="volume">21</biblScope>
                    <biblScope unit="issue">10</biblScope>
                  </imprint>
                </monogr>
                <ref type="url"
                  >http://www.columbia.edu/cu/record/archives/vol21/vol21_iss10/record2110.28.html</ref>
              </biblStruct>
            </note>
          </notesStmt>
          <!--<projectDesc> <creation when="1996">1996</creation> <country>États-Unis</country> <langUsage> <language ident="eng" usage="100">Anglais (langue principale)</language> </langUsage> <projectClass> <keywords xml:lang="fr" scheme="http://data.bnf.fr/liste-rameau"> <term url="http://catalogue.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/cb11934792v/PUBLIC" >Architecture gothique</term> <term>13e siècle</term> <term>France</term> </keywords> <keywords xml:lang="eng" scheme="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/about.html#lcsh"> <term url="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85006792" >Architecture, Gothic</term> <term url="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh2002012456">13th century</term> <term url="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n79006404" >France</term> </keywords> <classCode scheme="http://dublincore.org/documents/2012/06/14/dcmi-terms/"> <term>website</term> <!-\- TODO qualifier -\-> </classCode> </projectClass> -->
        </biblFull>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Hachiman Digital Handscrolls</title>
            <principal>
              <persName>
                <forename>Melanie</forename>
                <surname>Trede</surname>
              </persName>
              <roleName>Head of project</roleName>
              <orgName>Heidelberg University</orgName>
            </principal>
            <funder>Initiative d’excellence de l’université de Heidelberg, Field of Focus 3 Cultural
              Dynamics in Globalised Worlds sponsorisé par la Fondation allemande de recherche entre
              mars 2014 et février 2015. Le projet fut étendu et complété en octobre 2015 avec des
              fonds du responsable du projet.</funder>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Universität Heidelberg</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Allemagne</pubPlace>
            <date from="2014" to="2015">2014 à 2015</date>
            <idno>http://kjc-sv013.kjc.uni-heidelberg.de/hachiman/</idno>
          </publicationStmt>
          <notesStmt>
            <note type="abstract" xml:lang="fr">
              <p>Le but du picturalprojet consistait à rendre possible la présentation numérique de
                formats textuels et iconographiques longitudinaux et de pouvoir les les rendre
                accessibles à une large audience. La présentation explore les possibilités de
                visualisation simultanée d’un même thème iconographique ou textuel dans plusieurs
                sources.</p>
              <p>Le contenu pictural et textuel des rouleaux est identifié par des zones et indexé.
                Ce découpage permet une navigation hypertexteulle et de fournir des informations
                supplémentaire. Une table lumineuses permet de rassemblée des ensembles pour les
                étudier de manière adéquate.</p>
              <p>Techniquement, le site utilise le logiciel <ref target="http://hyperimage.ws"
                  >HyperImage Reader</ref>.</p>
            </note>
          </notesStmt>
        </biblFull>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Venus iconography</title>
            <principal>
              <persName>
                <forename>K.</forename>
                <surname>Bender</surname>
              </persName>
            </principal>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>K. Bender</publisher>
            <pubPlace>s.l.</pubPlace>
            <date from="2009" to="2014">2009 à 2014</date>
            <idno>https://sites.google.com/site/venusiconography/</idno>
            <idno type="internetArchive"
              >https://web.archive.org/web/20200808173853/https://sites.google.com/site/venusiconography/</idno>
          </publicationStmt>
          <notesStmt>
            <note type="abstract" xml:lang="fr">
              <p>Le projet propose une collection de recherche thématique pour contribuer à une
                lecture distante, à une macroanalyse et à une approche quantitative en histoire de
                l’art.</p>
              <p>Techniquement très simple, le site utilise le service <ref
                  target="https://sites.google.com">Google sites</ref>.</p>
            </note>
          </notesStmt>
        </biblFull>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Mapping Titian</title>
            <title type="sub">See the history of art by mapping Titian’s paintings across time and
              space</title>
            <principal>
              <persName>
                <forename>Jodi</forename>
                <surname>Cranston</surname>
              </persName>
              <persName>
                <forename>Antien</forename>
                <surname>Knaap</surname>
              </persName>
            </principal>
            <funder>Kress Foundation</funder>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Department of History of Art &amp; Architecture at Boston
              University</authority>
            <publisher>Boston University</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Boston</pubPlace>
            <date when="2015">2015</date>
            <idno>http://www.mappingtitian.org</idno>
            <idno type="internetArchive"
              >https://web.archive.org/web/20210927012903/http://www.mappingtitian.org/</idno>
          </publicationStmt>
          <notesStmt>
            <note type="abstract" xml:lang="fr">
              <p>Le projet propose une cartographie des œuvres du Titien. C’est un site collaboratif
                qui permet l’édition d’un catalogue d’œuvres et leur visualisation sur une
                carte.</p>
            </note>
          </notesStmt>
        </biblFull>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>The Digital Michelangelo Project</title>
            <principal>
              <persName>
                <forename>Marc</forename>
                <surname>Levoy</surname>
              </persName>
            </principal>
            <funder>Stanford University</funder>
            <funder>Interval Research Corporation</funder>
            <funder>Paul G. Allen Foundation for the Arts</funder>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Stanford University</authority>
            <publisher>University of Washington</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Stanford</pubPlace>
            <date from="1997" to="2004">1997 à 2004</date>
            <idno>http://graphics.stanford.edu/projects/mich/</idno>
          </publicationStmt>
          <notesStmt>
            <note type="abstract" xml:lang="en">
              <p>Recent improvements in laser rangefinder technology, together with algorithms
                developed at <orgName>Stanford</orgName> for combining multiple range and color
                images, allow us to reliably and accurately digitize the external shape and surface
                characteristics of many physical objects. Examples include machine parts, cultural
                artifacts, and design models for the manufacturing, moviemaking, and video game
                industries. As an application of this technology, a team of 30 faculty, staff, and
                students from <orgName>Stanford University</orgName> and <orgName>the University of
                  Washington</orgName> spent the 1998-99 academic year in Italy scanning the
                sculptures and architecture of Michelangelo. As a side project, we also scanned
                1,163 fragments of the Forma Urbis Romae, a giant marble map of ancient Rome. We are
                currently back in the United States processing the data we acquired. Our goal is to
                produce a set of 3D computer models - one for each statue, architectural setting,
                and map fragment we scanned - and to make these models available to scholars
                worldwide. The motivations behind this project are to advance the technology of 3D
                scanning, to place this technology in the service of the humanities, and to create a
                long-term digital archive of some important cultural artifacts. Our sponsors are
                  <orgName>Stanford University</orgName>, <orgName>Interval Research
                  Corporation</orgName> and <orgName>the Paul G. Allen Foundation for the
                  Arts</orgName>. Our collaborators, a mix of computer scientists and art
                historians, include the Italian museums and institutions whose names are listed
                below.</p>
            </note>
          </notesStmt>
        </biblFull>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Wired !</title>
            <title type="sub">Digital art history &amp; visual culture</title>
            <principal>
              <persName>
                <forename>Kristin Huffman</forename>
                <surname>Lanzoni</surname>
              </persName>
            </principal>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Duke University</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Duhram</pubPlace>
            <date from="2009" to="2015">2009 à 2015</date>
            <idno>http://www.dukewired.org</idno>
          </publicationStmt>
          <notesStmt>
            <note type="abstract" xml:lang="fr">
              <p>Wired ! est un groupe de chercheurs de l’univeristé de Duke qui appliquent les
                technologies de visualisation culturelle et historique et leurs méthodes à l’étude
                de la culture matérielle, de l’art, de l’architecture et à l’histoire urbaine.</p>
              <p>Le projet a changé de nom pour devenir le <title>Duke’s Digital Art History &amp; Visual
                  Culture Research Lab</title>.</p>
            </note>
          </notesStmt>
        </biblFull>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Forma Urbis Romae</title>
            <title type="sub">Pianta monumentale di Roma per il grande giubileo del 2000</title>
            <principal>
              <orgName>Biblioteca Apostolica Vaticana</orgName>
            </principal>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Biblioteca Apostolica Vaticana</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Cité du Vatican</pubPlace>
            <date when="2001">2001</date>
            <idno>http://www.vatican.va/formaurbis/index_fr.htm</idno>
          </publicationStmt>
          <notesStmt>
            <note type="abstract" xml:lang="it">
              <p>La Biblioteca Apostolica Vaticana in collaborazione con l’Istituto Nazionale per la
                Grafica ha realizzato, in occasione del Grande Giubileo dell'Anno Duemila, una
                Pianta di Roma incisa su rame ad acquaforte e bulino e stampata seguendo i
                procedimenti tradizionali della calcografia.</p>
            </note>
            <note type="projectBib">
              <biblStruct>
                <analytic>
                  <title type="a"> La Forma Urbis Romae, Bilan de vingt-cinq années de recherches </title>
                  <author>
                    <persName>
                      <forename>Charles</forename>
                      <surname>Davoine</surname>
                    </persName>
                  </author>
                </analytic>
                <monogr>
                  <title type="j">Histoire Urbaine</title>
                  <imprint>
                    <date when="2007">2007</date>
                    <biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
                    <biblScope unit="volume">20</biblScope>
                  </imprint>
                </monogr>
                <ref type="url">https://www.cairn.info/revue-histoire-urbaine-2007-3-page-133.htm</ref>
              </biblStruct>
            </note>
          </notesStmt>
        </biblFull>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Visualizing Venice</title>
            <title type="sub">Exploring the city’s past</title>
            <principal>
              <persName>
                <forename>Alessandra</forename>
                <surname>Ferrighi</surname>
              </persName>
              <persName>
                <forename>Kristin</forename>
                <surname>Lanzoni</surname>
              </persName>
              <persName>
                <forename>Cosimo</forename>
                <surname>Monteleone</surname>
              </persName>
              <persName>
                <forename>Elena</forename>
                <surname>Svalduz</surname>
              </persName>
            </principal>
            <funder>Gladys Krieble Delmas Foundation</funder>
            <funder>Fondazione di Venezia</funder>
            <funder>Regione del Veneto</funder>
            <funder>Bass Connections, Duke University</funder>
            <funder>Humanities Writ Large, Duke University</funder>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Duke University</authority>
            <authority>Università luav di Venezia</authority>
            <authority>Università degli Studi di Padova</authority>
            <pubPlace/>
            <!-- NEED INFO -->
            <date from="2009" to="2015">2015</date>
            <idno>http://www.visualizingvenice.org/visu/</idno>
          </publicationStmt>
          <noteStmt>
            <note type="abstract" xml:lang="">
              <p/>
              <!-- NEED INFO -->
            </note>
          </noteStmt>
        </biblFull>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>ArtStor</title>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>JStor</publisher>
            <idno>http://www.artstor.org/index.shtml</idno>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Rome reborn</title>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>frischerconsulting</publisher>
            <idno>http://romereborn.frischerconsulting.com</idno>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Online Scholarly Catalogue Initiative</title>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Getty</publisher>
            <idno>http://www.getty.edu/foundation/initiatives/current/osci/index.html</idno>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Raphael Research Resource</title>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher/>
            <idno>http://cima.ng-london.org.uk/documentation/</idno>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>SmartHistory</title>
            <funder>Khan academy</funder>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Khan Academy</publisher>
            <idno>https://www.khanacademy.org/humanities/art-history-basics/beginners-art-history/a/cave-painting-contemporary-art-and-everything-in-between</idno>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Song and Yuan Dynasty Painting and Calligraphy</title>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Freer Gallery of Art</authority>
            <publisher>The Smithsonian’s Museum of Asian Art</publisher>
            <idno>http://www.asia.si.edu/SongYuan/</idno>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Mapping Gothic France</title>
            <principal>
              <persName>
                <forename>Stephen</forename>
                <surname>Murray</surname>
              </persName>
              <persName>
                <forename>Andrew</forename>
                <surname>Tallon</surname>
              </persName>
              <persName>
                <forename>Rory</forename>
                <surname>O’Neill</surname>
              </persName>
            </principal>
            <funder>The Mellon Foundation</funder>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Media Center for Art History, Columbia University</authority>
            <authority>Art Department, Vassar College</authority>
            <publisher>Columbia University</publisher>
            <idno>http://mappinggothic.org</idno>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>FACES: Faces, Art, and Computerized Evaluation Systems, Phase II</title>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher/>
            <idno><![CDATA[https://securegrants.neh.gov/publicquery/main.aspx?f=1&gn=HD-51735-13]]></idno>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>The Digital Sculpture Project</title>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Virginia</publisher>
            <date from="2009" to="2013">2009 à 2013</date>
            <idno>http://www.digitalsculpture.org</idno>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Digging into Image Data to Answer Authorship-Related Questions (DID-ARQ)</title>
            <funder>National Science Foundation</funder>
            <funder>National Endowment for the Humanities</funder>
            <funder>Humanities Research Council</funder>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher/>
            <idno>http://isda.ncsa.illinois.edu/DID/</idno>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Ceramics in Mainland Southeast Asia</title>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Smithsonian, Freer Gallery of Art and Arthur M. Sackler Gallery</publisher>
            <date when="2008">2008</date>
            <idno>http://seasianceramics.asia.si.edu</idno>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Cranach Digital Archive</title>
            <funder>Andrew W. Mellon Foundation</funder>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Stiftung Museum Kunstpalast, Düsseldorf</publisher>
            <publisher>Cologne Institute of Conservation Sciences / Cologne University of Applied
              Sciences</publisher>
            <date from="2009" to="2018"/>
            <idno>http://www.lucascranach.org</idno>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Chapelle numérique</title>
            <principal>
              <persName>Bibliothèque Vaclav Havel</persName>
            </principal>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Bibliothèque Vaclav Havel</publisher>
            <date when="2015">c. 2015</date>
            <idno>http://umap.openstreetmap.fr/fr/map/chapelle-numerique_41723</idno>
          </publicationStmt>
          <notesStmt>
            <note>
              <p>La Chapelle numérique est un fonds documentaire sur le quartier de la Chapelle,
                dans le dix-huitième arrondissement de Paris. Il s’agit d’un projet amateur de
                collecte et de mise en commun de ressources numérisées libres de droits. Il s’agit
                de rendre justice de la richesse et de la diversité de ce quartier multiculturel et
                populaire parisien.</p>
              <p>Le projet utilise l’application <ref target="http://umap.openstreetmap.fr/"
                  >umap</ref> qui permet de créer des cartes personnalisées sur des fonds d’<ref
                  target="http://osm.org/">OpenStreetMap</ref></p>
            </note>
          </notesStmt>
        </biblFull>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Hidden Florence</title>
            <principal>
              <persName>
                <forename>Fabrizio</forename>
                <surname>Nevola</surname>
              </persName>
              <orgName>University of Exeter</orgName>
            </principal>
            <respStmt>
              <resp>auteur</resp>
              <persName>
                <forename>Fabrizio</forename>
                <surname>Nevola</surname>
              </persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
              <resp>auteur</resp>
              <persName>
                <forename>David</forename>
                <surname>Rosenthal</surname>
              </persName>
            </respStmt>
            <funder>the Arts &amp; Humanities Research Council (UK) (grant number
              AH/K005138/1)</funder>
            <funder>the HEFCE Higher Education Innovation Fund (HEIF) Open Innovation Fund pour le
              support dans la promotion de l’application et la création des films courts.</funder>
            <funder>Commune di Firenze</funder>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Exeter</publisher>
            <date when="2014">2014</date>
            <idno>http://hiddenflorence.org</idno>
          </publicationStmt>
          <notesStmt>
            <note>
              <p><title>Hidden Florence</title> est une application gratuite pour téléphone
                intelligent qui offre une visite de la ville à travers un guide fictif «
                contemporain » des années 1490 qui serait un ouvrier de l’industrie lainière.</p>
              <p>Le site designé par <ref target="http://kierongurner.co.uk/">Kieron Gurner</ref>
                est conçu avec WordPress. L’application a été développée par <ref
                  target="http://calvium.com">Calvium Ltd</ref></p>
            </note>
          </notesStmt>
        </biblFull>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Histoire du bâti Parisien</title>
            <title type="sub">Petite cartographie des périodes de construction du bâti parisien et
              des monuments historiques de la capitale</title>
            <principal>
              <persName>@comeetie</persName>
            </principal>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher><ref target="http://www.comeetie.fr">Commeetie</ref>
              <ref target="http://www.comeetie.fr">http://www.comeetie.fr</ref>
            </publisher>
            <date when="2015">2015</date>
            <idno>http://www.comeetie.fr/galerie/BatiParis/</idno>
          </publicationStmt>
          <notesStmt>
            <note>
              <p>Carte qui permet de naviguer entre les différentes strates du bâti parisien conçue
                à partir des données de l’<ref
                  target="http://www.apur.org/article/donnees-disponibles-open-data">APUR</ref>. Il
                est possible de filtrer les immeubles selon leur date d’édification, et obtenir des
                informations sur les architectes et les immeubles classées titrées de la base de
                données des monumenst historiques <ref
                  target="http://www.culture.gouv.fr/culture/inventai/patrimoine/">Mérimée</ref>
                géolocalisées grâce à Wikimedia Commons.</p>
            </note>
          </notesStmt>
        </biblFull>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">The Paintings of Paul Cézanne</title>
            <title type="sub">An online catalogue raisonné under the direction of Walter
              Feilchenfeldt, Jayne Warman and David Nash</title>
            <principal>
              <persName>
                <forename>Walter</forename>
                <surname>Feilchenfeldt</surname>
              </persName>
            </principal>
            <principal>
              <persName>
                <forename>Jayne</forename>
                <surname>Warman</surname>
              </persName>
            </principal>
            <principal>
              <persName>
                <forename>David</forename>
                <surname>Nash</surname>
              </persName>
            </principal>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Copyright 2016 Cézanne Online Catalogue, LLC. All Rights Reserved</publisher>
            <date when="2014-10-06">6 octobre 2014</date>
            <idno>http://www.cezannecatalogue.com</idno>
          </publicationStmt>
          <notesStmt>
            <note>
              <p>Ce catalogue raisonné est une tentative de rendre compte de l’œuvre complet du
                peintre. Le projet tire parti de la versatilité des technologies numériques et
                entend orienter la recherche sur le peintre dans de nouvelles voies. Le catalogue en
                ligne est interactif et peut être mis à jour de manière régulière afin que les
                utilisateurs soient assurés de toujours y trouver une information à jour. Les
                auteurs espèrent ainsi que ce catalogue bénéficie grandement aux chercheurs et aux
                étudiants qui pourront ainsi largement avoir accès à des recherches avancées et
                sauvegarder leurs résultats.</p>
              <p>Le catalogue en ligne résulte d’un effort collaboratif. L’intérêt d’un catalogue en
                ligne consistant à le rendre largement consultable et à ses possibilités aisées de
                mise à jour.</p>
              <p>Design du site web et logiciel de base de données par <ref
                  target="http://panopticondesign.net/">panOpticon</ref></p>
            </note>
          </notesStmt>
        </biblFull>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>QRator</title>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>A joint project with UCL Centre for Digital Humanities, Centre for Advanced
              Spatial Analysis and UCL Museums</publisher>
            <date when="2011">2011</date>
            <idno>http://www.qrator.org</idno>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Past visions</title>
            <title type="sub">penned by Frederick William IV</title>
            <principal>
              <persName>
                <forename>Marian</forename>
                <surname>Dörk</surname>
              </persName>
            </principal>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher/>
            <date when="2016">2016</date>
            <idno>http://uclab.fh-potsdam.de/fw4/en/</idno>
          </publicationStmt>
          <notesStmt>
            <note>
              <p>This website and the visualisation prototype are being developed within the
                framework of the research project <ref
                  target="http://uclab.fh-potsdam.de/projects/vikus/">»VIKUS - Visualising Cultural
                  Collections«</ref> that is funded by the Federal Ministry of Education and
                Research. Project partners are the Prussian Palaces and Gardens Foundation
                Berlin-Brandenburg (SPSG) and the Programmfabrik GmbH.</p>
              <p>The visualisation is based on an online inventory catalogue of the drawings by
                Frederick William IV of Prussia. It was published in 2013 by the Prussian Palaces
                and Gardens Foundation Berlin-Brandenburg (SPSG). The SPSG received funding for the
                research and publishing of the online inventory catalogue by the German Research
                Foundation (DFG) the Reinhold and Elisabeth-Schulze-Foundation, the
                Scherping-Schulze-Foundation and the Fritz Thyssen Foundation.</p>
              <p>The digital copies, metadata, and texts used in the visualisation were created by
                Dr. Jörg Meiner (project lead), Dr. Catharina Hasenclever (project lead 2006-2008),
                Antje Adler, Astrid Fritsche, Klaus Dorst, Stefan Gehlen, Dr. Gabriele Horn, Dr.
                Andreas Meinecke, Dr. Gerd-H. Zuchold, Dr. Rolf H. Johannsen, Prof. Dr. Harry Falk,
                Dr. Rolf Th. Senn and Dr. Sepp-Gustav Gröschel. Editor: Dr. Carsten Dilba.</p>
              <p>The timeline information was supplemented with excerpts from the exhibition
                catalogue »Unglaublich ist sein Genie fürs Zeichnen« Friedrich Wilhelm IV. von
                Preußen (1795-1861) zum 150. Todestag, published on behalf of the Prussian Palaces
                and Gardens Foundation Berlin-Brandenburg by Jörg Meiner, 2011.</p>
              <p>TECHNOLOGY : HTML5, CSS3, Canvas/WebGL, pixi.js und d3.js</p>
            </note>
          </notesStmt>
        </biblFull>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">London Gallery Project</title>
            <principal>
              <persName>
                <forename>Pamela</forename>
                <surname>Fletcher</surname>
              </persName>
            </principal>
            <respStmt>
              <resp>Second Investigator and Technical Advisor</resp>
              <persName>
                <forename>David</forename>
                <surname>Israel</surname>
              </persName>
            </respStmt>
            <funder>Funding for the project was provided by the <ref target="http://nitle.org/"
                  ><orgName>National Institute for Technology and Liberal Education</orgName></ref>,
              with student support from the Gibbons Summer Research Internship Fund, and the Bowdoin
              College Office of Information Technology.</funder>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Bowdoin Art History Department</publisher>
            <date from="2007" to="2012">2007-2012</date>
            <idno>http://19thc-artworldwide.org/fletcher/london-gallery/</idno>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Vistas</title>
            <title type="sub">Visual Culture in Spanish America, 1520-1820</title>
            <principal>
              <persName>
                <forename>Dana</forename>
                <surname>Leibsohn</surname>
              </persName>
            </principal>
            <principal>
              <persName>
                <forename>Barbara E.</forename>
                <surname>Mundy</surname>
              </persName>
            </principal>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher/>
            <idno>https://vistas.ace.fordham.edu</idno>
            <date from="2005" to="2015">2005-2015</date>
          </publicationStmt>
          <notesStmt>
            <note>
              <p>The Vistas project seeks to bring an understanding of the visual culture of Spanish
                America to a broad audience. Spanish America was an extensive region—covering much
                of the Americas, running from California to Chile from the 16th century to the early
                19th century. Its visual culture was forged in urban centers, religious and frontier
                communities, and indigenous towns. The new Vistas website offers a gallery of
                high-resolution color images, each of them fully annotated, videos and interpretive
                essays on Vista’s six themes, along with discussion of related images. In the
                “Library” and “Texts” sections are primary documents relating to visual culture,
                with discussions and bibliography. Other features are seen in the sidebar.</p>
              <p>This site was last updated in April 2015, with new design, addition of
                library/texts and Luna galleries.</p>
              <p>http://www.smith.edu/vistas/ Copyright 2005, Dana Leibsohn and Barbara Mundy Please
                credit as: Leibsohn, Dana, and Barbara Mundy, Vistas: Visual Culture in Spanish
                America, 1520-1820. http://www.smith.edu/vistas, 2005.</p>
              <p>This website supersedes an earlier Spanish-English one, which remains visible at
                www.smith.edu/vistas.</p>
              <p> Vistas has been created with support from the <ref target="http://www.neh.fed.us/"
                  >National Endowment for the Humanities</ref>, and the <ref
                  target="http://www.inah.gob.mx/">Instituto Nacional de Antropología e
                  Historia</ref>.</p>
            </note>
          </notesStmt>
        </biblFull>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>The Corpus of Medieval Narrative Art</title>
            <principal>
              <persName>
                <forename>Stuart</forename>
                <surname>Whatling</surname>
              </persName>
            </principal>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher/>
            <idno>http://www.medievalart.org.uk</idno>
            <date from="2006" to="2010">2006 à 2010</date>
          </publicationStmt>
          <notesStmt>
            <note>
              <p>Ce site web est un entrepôt de photographies réalisées par l’auteur entre 2006 et
                2010 dans le cadre de son travail de recherche doctorale.</p>
            </note>
          </notesStmt>
        </biblFull>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Pompei. La fortuna visiva</title>
            <title type="sub">Achivio di immagini e testi dal XVIII al XIX secolo</title>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher/>
            <idno>http://pompei.sns.it</idno>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Verspera</title>
            <author>
              <orgName>Fondation des Sciences du Patrimoine</orgName>
            </author>
            <author>
              <persName>
                <forename>Mathieu </forename>
                <surname>da Vinha</surname>
              </persName>
              <!-- ingénieur de recherche, directeur scientifique, Centre de recherche du château de Versailles -->
            </author>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Fondation des Sciences du Patrimoine</publisher>
            <pubPlace>France</pubPlace>
            <date from="2012">2012-</date>
            <idno>http://verspera.hypotheses.org</idno>
          </publicationStmt>
          <notesStmt>
            <note>
              <p>Le projet de recherche « VERSPERA », porté par la Fondation des Sciences du
                Patrimoine. Celui-ci vise à rendre publics les plans du domaine de Versailles sous
                l’Ancien Régime et à en restituer certains espaces grâce à la modélisation 3D. Le
                corpus numérisé est conservé aux Archives nationales (Paris), à la Bibliothèque
                nationale de France et à l’Établissement public du château, du musée et du domaine
                national de Versailles. Ce projet répond à trois objectifs : préserver des fonds
                fragiles et difficilement accessibles, en faciliter l’accès via Internet à la
                communauté internationale scientifique interdisciplinaire et permettre, grâce à la
                modélisation, une réflexion sur l’utilisation qui pouvait être faite d’une résidence
                royale à l’époque moderne.</p>
            </note>
          </notesStmt>
        </biblFull>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Zeitreise</title>
            <title>Das Stadel Museum im 19. jahrundert</title>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Stadel Museum</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Germany</pubPlace>
            <idno>http://zeitreise.staedelmuseum.de</idno>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Emblematica Online</title>
            <funder ref="http://www.neh.gov/">National Endowment for the Humanities</funder>
            <funder ref="http://www.dfg.de/">Deutsche Forschungsgemeinschaft</funder>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Illinois Board of Trustees</publisher>
            <date from="2010" to="2015">2010-2015</date>
            <idno>http://emblematica.grainger.illinois.edu</idno>
          </publicationStmt>
          <notesStmt>
            <note>
              <p>Discover the early modern world of texts and images here!</p>
              <p>Emblematica Online draws from the most important collections of emblematica
                worldwide. It is hosted by the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign, and its
                founding partner is the Herzog August Bibliothek, Wolfenbüttel. Contributing
                partners include Glasgow University Library and Utrecht University, which
                contributed both book- and emblem-level data. Additional contributors include the
                Getty Research Institute Library and Duke University Library, both of which
                contributed book-level information.</p>
            </note>
          </notesStmt>
        </biblFull>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title xml:lang="de">Kupferstichkabinett online</title>
            <title xml:lang="en">Virtual Printroom online</title>
            <funder>
              <orgName>Niedersächsisches Ministerium für Wissenschaft und Kultur</orgName>
              <date from="2018-04" to="2020-09">avril 2018 à septembre 2020</date>
            </funder>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>
              <orgName>Herzog August Bibliothek (HAB)</orgName>
              <placeName>Wolfenbüttel</placeName>
            </publisher>
            <publisher>
              <orgName ref="http://www.haum.niedersachsen.de/">Herzog Anton Ulrich Museum
                (HAUM)</orgName>
              <placeName>Braunschweig</placeName>
            </publisher>
            <idno>http://diglib.hab.de/?link=046</idno>
            <idno>http://www.virtuelles-kupferstichkabinett.de</idno>
          </publicationStmt>
          <notesStmt>
            <note>
              <p>The aim of the project is to create a virtual combination of a representative
                selection of items from the print collections of both institutions. These include
                holdings which once belonged to the former ducal collections, but are now divided
                between the HAUM and the HAB. The main focus will be on works dating from before
                1850. In the first project phase more than 37,000 prints have been digitalised and
                described. In this project phase additional 8,000 grafic sheets shall be digitalised
                and described, among them sheets from volumes of the dukes Julius, Heinrich Julius
                and August and of the graphic and topographic collections. Descriptions and linked
                images will be entered into a database which will be freely available via the
                internet. Formal descriptions will be based on international standards. In addition
                all imprints will be indexed by Foto Marburg using Iconclass. The database will be
                accessible via a common internet portal of the HAUM and HAB, as well as through the
                indexes of the archives of Bildarchiv Foto Marburg.</p>
            </note>
          </notesStmt>
        </biblFull>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Virtual St. Paul’s cathedral project</title>
            <title type="sub">A digital re-creation of worship and preaching at St. Paul’s cathedral
              in early modern London</title>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>NC State University</publisher>
            <date/>
            <idno>https://vpcp.chass.ncsu.edu</idno>
          </publicationStmt>
          <notesStmt>
            <note>
              <p>The Virtual St Paul’s Cathedral Project will enable us to experience worship and
                preaching at St Paul’s Cathedral and in Paul’s Churchyard as events that unfold over
                time and on particular occasions in London in the early seventeenth century.</p>
              <p>In time, this site will host a visual model of St Paul’s Cathedral and the
                surrounding churchyard, together with a recreation of worship for Easter Sunday
                1624, with all the liturgical events of the day, including choir and organ music
                plus a sermon in the morning by Bishop Lancelot Andrewes and a sermon in the
                afternoon by John Donne, Dean of the cathedral.</p>
              <p>For now, the site hosts the first phase of this project, the Virtual Paul’s Cross
                Project, which has already been completed. This Project provides the experience of
                hearing John Donne’s sermon for Gunpowder Day, November 5th, 1622 in Paul’s
                Churchyard, the specific physical location for which it was composed.</p>
            </note>
          </notesStmt>
        </biblFull>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Ed Ruscha Streets of Los Angeles Project</title>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Getty Researche Institute</publisher>
            <date from="2018" to="2020">[2018]-2020</date>
            <idno>http://www.getty.edu/research/scholars/digital_art_history/index.html</idno>
          </publicationStmt>
          <notesStmt>
            <note>
              <p>This project digitizes a pioneering collection generated by one of the world's most
                recognized artists. The innovative digitization and exhibition of this archive will
                make public for the first time a resource for scholars of history, art,
                architecture, and urban studies, available in 2020.</p>
            </note>
          </notesStmt>
        </biblFull>

        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Getty Scholars’ Workspace™</title>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Getty</publisher>
            <date from="2014" to="2016">[2014]-2016</date>
            <idno>http://www.getty.edu/research/scholars/digital_art_history/getty_scholars_workspace/index.html</idno>
          </publicationStmt>
          <notesStmt>
            <note>
              <p>Getty Scholars' Workspace™ is an online environment designed to support
                collaborative art-historical research. It provides a space and a toolset that enable
                research teams to examine digital surrogates of works of art and primary source
                materials, build a bibliography, translate and annotate texts, and exchange ideas.
                With Scholars' Workspace, research and communication are consolidated into a single
                online location accessible from anywhere.</p>
            </note>
          </notesStmt>
        </biblFull>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title/>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Getty</publisher>
            <date from="2017">2017</date>
            <idno>https://github.com/thegetty/mutual-muses</idno>
            <idno>https://thegetty.github.io/mutual-muses</idno>
          </publicationStmt>
          <notesStmt>
            <note>
              <p>Mutual Muses is a crowdsourced transcription project undertaken by the Digital Art
                History program at the Getty Research Institute in 2017. The project crowdsourced
                transcriptions of correspondence from the archives of art critic Lawrence Alloway
                (1926-1990) and feminist artist Sylvia Sleigh (ca. 1916-2010), which are held at the
                Getty Research Institute. These letters reveal the intimate early stages of their
                respective careers and intertwined personal lives in postwar England from 1948-1953.
                The results of this project include transcription data for 2,376 documents from
                these archives, as well as code used for processing and analyzing the data results
                and producing file outputs.</p>
            </note>
            <note><p>This publication uses data generated via the <ref
                  target="http://www.zooniverse.org">Zooniverse platform</ref>.</p></note>
          </notesStmt>
        </biblFull>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Digital Serlio</title>
            <funder>Sidney J. Weinberg, Jr. Foundation</funder>
            <funder>Samuel Freeman Charitable Trust</funder>
            <editor>
              <persName>
                <forename>Francesco</forename>
                <surname>Benelli</surname>
              </persName>
            </editor>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>The Italian Academy for advanced studies in America, Columbia
              University</publisher>
            <date>2018</date>
            <idno>http://italianacademy.columbia.edu/digital-serlio-project</idno>
          </publicationStmt>
          <notesStmt>
            <note>
              <p>The Digital Serlio project establishes online access to Avery Classics' corpus of
                Sebastiano Serlio editions and his unpublished manuscript "On Domestic Architecture"
                (Tutte l'opere d'architettura, Libro VI, 1619). Research for this project is being
                conducted in Getty Scholars' Workspace v 1.1.</p>
              <p>An international team of scholars is coordinated by Prof. Francesco Benelli, while
                scholars and staff at the Avery Library direct the effort in collaboration with the
                Graduate School of Architecture, Planning and Preservation (GSAPP), and the Italian
                Academy, all at Columbia, as well as Avery Friends, the University of Bologna and
                the École nationale des Chartes. Digital photography and project support are
                provided by the Avery Digital Lab and (also within Columbia's Libraries) the Digital
                Program Division and the Preservation and Digital Conversion Division.</p>
            </note>
          </notesStmt>
        </biblFull>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Resonating Spaces: Hans Scharoun's Berlin Philharmonie in 3-D</title>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Getty</publisher>
            <date when="2017">2017</date>
            <idno>http://www.getty.edu/research/exhibitions_events/exhibitions/space_for_music/</idno>
          </publicationStmt>
          <notesStmt>
            <note>
              <p>Using laser-scanning technology, this project examines Hans Scharoun’s iconic
                Berlin Philharmonie (1960–1963) through 3-D renderings. The project’s first phase, a
                collaboration with the Fraunhofer Institute’s Competence Center for Cultural
                Heritage Digitization, produced a physical model of the hall, which was featured in
                the exhibition Berlin/LA: Spaces for Music.</p>
            </note>
          </notesStmt>
        </biblFull>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Mnemosyne. Meanderings through Aby Warburg’s Atlas</title>
            <editor>
              <persName>
                <surname>Christopher D.</surname>
                <forename>Johnson</forename>
              </persName>
            </editor>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Cornell University</publisher>
            <date from="2013" to="2016">2013-2016</date>
            <idno>https://warburg.library.cornell.edu/</idno>
          </publicationStmt>
          <notesStmt>
            <note>
              <p>This website presents ten of these photographed panels, selected to exemplify both
                the cosmographical and art-historical content of the Mnemosyne Atlas. Though
                offering but fragments of a fragment, it is designed to show some of the
                Wanderstrassen that Warburg pursued in the Atlas. The Warburg Institute has provided
                new, better scans of the surviving photographs – better, that is, than the images
                seen in the Gesammelte Schriften volume and other publications (to say nothing of
                other venues on the Web).</p>
              <p>Furthermore, the ability to zoom in and out on the panels and on individual images
                permits a closer inspection of the material aspects of the Atlas. Alternately, if
                you click on individual images, a window providing identifying information will
                appear; frequently links to further iterations and permutations on the same image
                are also provided. Finally, under the tab “Guided Panels,” the user will find
                interpretations of individual panels by myself and other scholars. Such meanderings,
                of course, are meant to be at best exemplary, but never exhaustive.</p>
            </note>
          </notesStmt>
        </biblFull>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Artigo Social Image Tagging</title>
            <editor>
              <persName>
                <forename>Hubertus</forename>
                <surname>Kohle</surname></persName>
              <orgName>LMU Munich</orgName>
            </editor>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>LMU Munich</publisher>
            <idno>https://www.artigo.org</idno>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Itinera</title>
            <editor>
              <persName ref="http://www.dhrx.pitt.edu/2012/11/drew-armstrong/">
                <forename>Christopher Drew</forename>
                <surname>Armstrong</surname>
                <roleName>Academic Director</roleName>
              </persName>
            </editor>
            <editor>
              <persName ref="http://www.dhrx.pitt.edu/2012/11/alison-langmead/">
                <forename>Alison</forename>
                <surname>Langmead</surname>
              </persName>
              <roleName>Technical Director</roleName>
            </editor>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Pittsburgh</publisher>
            <idno>https://itinera.pitt.edu</idno>
          </publicationStmt>
          <notesStmt>
            <note>
              <p>Travel played a pivotal role in the shaping of the intellectual and artistic
                culture of eighteenth- and nineteenth-century Europe. While capital cities such as
                Rome, Paris, and London served as major attractions for travelers, the increasing
                specialization and ease of mobility over the course of these centuries drove
                exploration into remote areas such as Greece, Egypt, and the Near East.
                Simultaneously, an interest in “national” landscapes and antiquities made
                infrequently trafficked local regions the focus of new forms of tourism. The
                ramifications of this expansion of cultural tourism during the eighteenth and
                nineteenth centuries have been the subject of recent scholarly debates since, and
                Itinera offers a platform through which contemporary interests may engage with these
                issues.</p>
              <p>Visualizing, understanding, and generating new insights into the changing patterns
                and objectives for these types of travel are the primary motivators of behind
                Itinera. Designed to allow scholars and students to better comprehend the
                interconnected phenomena of mobility, object collection, and site documentation in
                the eighteenth and nineteenth centuries, Itinera is an map-based, interactive,
                digital resource that overlays and juxtaposes the movements of travelers alongside
                the objects of their study and their own creative output. Itinera therefore operates
                on between two central modelings. The “Travelers” section introduces a user of this
                site to the historical network in which individual agents existed, while the
                “Routes” and “Chronology” sections sketch the travels undertaken during their
                lifetimes.</p>
              <p>This digital environment has been proactively developed to collect and present
                historical data within a richly and transparently-structured visual context. Itinera
                presents the opportunity for academics and enthusiasts alike to engage with the
                phenomena of cultural tourism through an innovative academic apparatus. These
                visualizations not only account for the pre-existing scholarship on individual
                tours, but more crucially, Itinera promotes user-centric inquiry into the creation
                of meaningful historical relationships among people, objects, and sites.</p>
            </note>
          </notesStmt>
        </biblFull>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">EAT data scape</title>
            <title type="sub">1962-Today. An Exploration of the Experiments in Art and Technology
              Archives</title>
            <principal>
              <persName>
                <forename>Christophe</forename>
                <surname>Leclercq</surname>
              </persName>
              <roleName>art historian, project lead (research)</roleName>
            </principal>
            <principal>
              <persName>
                <forename>Paul</forename>
                <surname>Girard</surname>
              </persName>
              <roleName>engineer, project lead (technology and methodology)</roleName>
            </principal>
            <principal>
              <persName>
                <forename>Patrick</forename>
                <surname>Browne</surname>
              </persName>
              <roleName>intern engineer, development of the information system</roleName>
            </principal>
            <principal>
              <persName>
                <forename>Daniele</forename>
                <surname>Guido</surname>
              </persName>
              <roleName>designer, design and development of the visualization interfaces</roleName>
            </principal>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Sciences Po médialab</publisher>
            <date from="2010">depuis 2010</date>
            <idno>http://jiminy.medialab.sciences-po.fr/eat_datascape/</idno>
          </publicationStmt>
          <notesStmt>
            <note>Experiments in Art and Technology (E.A.T.) is a renowned example of
              interdisciplinarity at the intersection of Art, Science and Technology, conceived by
              Rauschenberg, a co-founder of E.A.T., as a « map of engineers, money and equipment »,
              facilitating collaborations between artist, engineer and industry. Despite the amount
              of information available, E.A.T.’s production and legacy remains unclear. The project,
              in collaboration with E.A.T. (represented by Julie Martin), is based on the
              organization’s numerous activities, developed in art and non-art contexts, including
              realized and unrealized works and projects from the 1960s to the present day. through
              a ‘datascape’. In the first place, the aim is to describe as extensively as possible
              the stories of works of art or projects, from their design and development stages to
              their different exhibitions and receptions. One of the main challenges is to produce a
              digital archive displaying the process of collaboration, not merely catalogue E.A.T.’s
              productions. Secondly, the archive will map these works and projects as networks of
              people, organizations, places and technologies, so as to better understand E.A.T.’s
              identity using the theories of Science and Technology Studies. The aim is to develop
              an online archive built as a research tool for humanities scholars in art and social
              art history. Their work, mapping the material in the archive, will provide the
              project’s added value; historical documents combined into information networks,
              revealed by various visualizations, will make of the archive a veritable exploratory
              tool.</note>
          </notesStmt>
        </biblFull>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Replica</title>
            <principal>
              <persName>
                <forename>Isabella</forename>
                <surname>di Lenardo</surname>
                <roleName>Project Head, Collaboratrice Scientifique, EPFL</roleName>
              </persName>
            </principal>
            <principal>
              <persName>
                <forename>Benoît</forename>
                <surname>Seguin</surname>
              </persName>
              <roleName>Ph.D. Student, EPFL</roleName>
            </principal>
            <principal>
              <persName>
                <forename>Frédéric </forename>
                <surname>Kaplan</surname>
              </persName>
              <roleName>Director DHLAB, EPFL</roleName>
            </principal>
            <principal>
              <persName>
                <forename>Carlotta</forename>
                <surname>Striolo</surname>
              </persName>
              <roleName>Intern, DHLAB - EPFL</roleName>
            </principal>
            <principal>
              <persName>
                <forename>Lia</forename>
                <surname>Costiner</surname>
              </persName>
              <roleName>Post Doc, DHLAB - EPFL</roleName>
            </principal>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>DHLAB (EPFL)</publisher>
            <date from="2015" to="2019">2015-2019</date>
            <idno>https://dhlab.epfl.ch/page-128334-en.html</idno>
          </publicationStmt>
          <notesStmt>
            <note>
              <p>How can digital tools assist researchers in the study of works of art? How can such
                tools help the general public explore, discover and connect to our cultural and
                artistic past?</p>
              <p>The digitization of millions of artworks by museums, libraries and cultural
                institution brings unprecedented access and opportunity to engage with collections.
                It also poses new challenges in the search, retrieval, and analysis of visual
                material. Currently, online databases of art can only be searched through keywords,
                or tags, namely the textual metadata of the original object. Textual queries,
                however, are not designed to search visual information which has not been indexed –
                they cannot for instance find similar shapes, forms, or motifs. This is why a new
                tool for searching art through its visual attributes is needed.</p>
              <p>The Replica project led by the DHLAB aims to build the first search engine designed
                specifically for the search and exploration of artistic collections (including
                paintings, drawings, engravings, sculpture and photography). This employs the latest
                state-of-the art artificial intelligence techniques, such as Deep Learning and
                Convolutional Neural Networks, for the search and display of information.</p>
              <p>In partnership with the Giorgio Cini Foundation in Venice and Factum Arte in
                Madrid, the Replica project aims to digitize roughly one million artistic
                reproductions using these images to populate the new search engine and as the basis
                for new art historical inquiries.</p>
              <p>Adam Lowe and Factum Arte have been collaborating with the Fondazione Giorgio Cini
                for a long time and have now built a specially designed circular scanning system,
                capable of recording 12 A3 sized double sided images at 400DPI per minute. The
                paired images are automatically downloaded with metadata tags and archived. The
                scanner is also equipped with a system of automatic object detection, a controlled
                light source and instant visualization of the images as they are being recorded.</p>
              <p>Replica opens new avenues for exploring and engaging with artistic collections. It
                assists art historians in the study of iconography, the transmission of forms,
                styles and patterns, while engaging larger audiences in a process of learning and
                discovery.</p>
            </note>
          </notesStmt>
        </biblFull>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Mapping the Republic of Letters</title>
            <title>British Architects on the Grand Tour</title>
            <principal>
              <forename>Giovanna</forename>
              <surname>Ceserani</surname>
            </principal>
            <funder>
              <orgName>NEH</orgName>
            </funder>
            <funder>
              <orgName>Stanford Presidential Fund for Innovation in the Humanities grants</orgName>
            </funder>
            <funder>
              <date from="2013">depuis 2013</date>
              <orgName>Cesta</orgName>
            </funder>
            <funder>
              <date when="2016">2016</date>
              <orgName>Roberta Bowman Denning Innovation in the Humanities Grant</orgName>
              <orgName>Stanford of the Faculty Dean of Research, Classics Department, the History
                Department, the Humanities Center, the Europe Center</orgName>
              <orgName>New Directions Mellon Fellowship.</orgName>
            </funder>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Stanford’s Center for Spatial and Textual Analysis</publisher>
            <date from="2008">2008</date>
            <idno>https://grandtour.stanford.edu</idno>
          </publicationStmt>
          <notesStmt>
            <note>
              <p>The Grand Tour Project began in 2008, when Giovanna Ceserani established it as one
                of the case studies within Mapping the Republic of Letters, the Stanford digital
                project dedicated to investigating early modern networks of knowledge through
                sophisticated digital approaches. The Grand Tour Project continues this mission
                while focusing on eighteenth-century travels to Italy, and, now based within CESTA
                (Stanford's Center for Spatial and Textual Analysis), it maintains close links to
                Mapping Republic of Letters and other Cesta research clusters such as the Spatial
                History Project and Humanities+Design. While remaining based in Stanford, where it
                has involved over the years many undergraduate and graduate researchers, faculty and
                staff, it has also expanded its collaborations internationally, as exemplified by
                its workshops (see People and Workshops). The Grand Tour Project is made possible
                thanks to generous institutional encouragement detailed at Project Support.</p>
            </note>
          </notesStmt>
        </biblFull>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Francis Towne</title>
            <title>A Catalogue Raisonné of Francis Towne (1739-1816)</title>
            <editor>
              <persName>
                <forename>Richard</forename>
                <surname>Stephens</surname>
              </persName>
            </editor>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Paul Mellon Centre</publisher>
            <date>2006-2016</date>
            <idno>http://francistowne.ac.uk</idno>
          </publicationStmt>
          <notesStmt>
            <note>
              <p>In 2006 Richard Stephens was awarded a PhD at Birkbeck College, London, for his
                thesis, A Catalogue Raisonné of The Works of Francis Towne, on which this website is
                based. In 2016 he curated the exhibition Light, Time, Legacy: Francis Towne's
                watercolours of Rome at the British Museum, London. He edits The art world in
                Britain 1660 to 1735, published by the University of York.</p>
            </note>
          </notesStmt>
        </biblFull>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Renaissance Polychrome Sculpture in Tuscany Database</title>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher/>
            <date>2019</date>
            <idno>http://qspace.library.queensu.ca/handle/1974/14832</idno>
          </publicationStmt>
          <notesStmt>
            <note>
              <p>is an online open-access database of photographs of and information about over 350
                objects, produced by Una D'Elia, Heather Merla, and Rachel Boyd. High-resolution
                photographs are freely available for research, teaching, and publication. Clicking
                on “show full item record” reveals further information and bibliography. The
                database also includes an integrated map, color-coded by material (by Claire Litt).
                For an example of how this resource can be used in teaching, see Reconstructing the
                Social Lives of Italian Renaissance Sculptures
                (reconstructingrenaissance.home.blog), a virtual exhibition created by Queen’s
                University undergraduate students, which includes digital visual reconstructions</p>
            </note>
          </notesStmt>
        </biblFull>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>The Watercolour World</title>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>The Watercolour World</publisher>
            <date>2019</date>
            <idno>https://www.watercolourworld.org</idno>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>The Digital Piranesi</title>
            <editor>
              <persName>
                <forename>Jeanne</forename>
                <surname>Britton</surname>
              </persName>
            </editor>
            <funder>
              <orgName>NEH grant from the Division of Preservation and Access</orgName>
              <date from="2019" to="2021">2019-2021</date>
            </funder>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of South Carolina (Columbia)</publisher>
            <date from="2019">2019-</date>
          </publicationStmt>
          <notesStmt>
            <note>
              <p>The Digital Piranesi (digitalpiranesi.org) is based at the University of South
                Carolina (Columbia), where the Irvin Department of Rare Books and Special
                Collections owns a rare full 29-volume set of Piranesi’s complete works. The project
                aims to make this interdisciplinary material accessible in a complete digital
                collection and, in an interactive digital edition, to illuminate and enact many of
                the graphic features of his innovative designs.</p>
            </note>
          </notesStmt>
        </biblFull>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Mapping Paintings</title>
            <funder>Kress foundation</funder>
            <editor>
              <persName>
                <forename>Jodi</forename>
                <surname>Cranston</surname>
              </persName>
            </editor>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Boston University</publisher>
            <date when="2021">2021</date>
          </publicationStmt>
          <notesStmt>
            <note>
              <p>Mapping Paintings is an open-source platform that allows users to tailor-make their
                own individual scholarly mapping projects. The platform facilitates the realization
                of these types of projects with an easy uploading of data collected and assembled by
                scholars without the need for learning GIS or other technologies. Although we have
                limited the platform in concept to paintings, users can include paintings, drawings,
                and prints—and really any artwork. Users can make their projects private or public.
                The uploaded data, once approved by our admin team, becomes part of the global
                library, which is available to all users of the site.</p>
              <p>The project is a scaled up version of Mapping Titian (www.mappingtitian.org), which
                is still useable; the data from that site is also available on Mapping Paintings.
                The data for the Titian project continues to be refined and edited, and users of
                Mapping Paintings are similarly encouraged to submit their data for in-progress
                projects.</p>
              <p>The platform is created and administered by Jodi Cranston (cranston@bu.edu),
                Professor, Department of History of Art &amp; Architecture, Boston University;
                developed by the software team at Prela, LLC; and generously funded by the Kress
                Foundation and Boston University.</p>
              <p>We are always looking for collaborators, whether individuals or institutions!
                Please join our community!</p>
            </note>
          </notesStmt>
        </biblFull>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Images of Rome</title>
            <title type="sub">The Rodolfo Lanciani Digital Archive</title>
            <principal>
              <persName>
                <forename>Giovanni</forename>
                <surname>Svevo</surname>
              </persName>
            </principal>
            <respStmt>
              <resp>curation of the selected material</resp>
              <persName>
                <forename>Nicola</forename>
                <surname>Camerlenghi</surname>
              </persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
              <resp>assistance</resp>
              <persName>
                <forename>Erik</forename>
                <surname>Steiner</surname>
              </persName>
            </respStmt>
            <funder ref="http://www.kressfoundation.org">Samuel H. Kress Foundation</funder>
            <sponsor ref="http://www.inasa-roma.it">Istituto Nazionale di Archeologia e Storia
              dell’Arte (INASA)</sponsor>
            <sponsor ref="http://www.archeologica.librari.beniculturali.it">Polo Museale del Lazio -
              Biblioteca di Archeologia e Storia dell’Arte (BIASA)</sponsor>
            <sponsor ref="http://uoregon.edu">University of Oregon</sponsor>
            <sponsor ref="http://dartmouth.edu">Dartmouth College</sponsor>
            <sponsor ref="https://cesta.stanford.edu">Stanford University, Center for Spatial and
              Textual Analysis (CESTA)</sponsor>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Stanford University Libraries (SUL)</publisher>
            <date from="2014" to="2016">2015-2016</date>
            <idno>https://exhibits.stanford.edu/lanciani/about/acknowledgements</idno>
          </publicationStmt>
          <notesStmt>
            <note>
              <quote><p>This website offers virtual access to a premier collection of historic
                  depictions amassed by Rodolfo Lanciani (1845–1929). Archaeologist, professor of
                  topography, and secretary of the Archaeological Commission, Lanciani was a pioneer
                  in the systematic, modern study of the city of Rome. Beginning in the latter part
                  of the nineteenth century and continuing into the first three decades of the
                  twentieth century, his work profoundly influenced our understanding of the ancient
                  city. Throughout his long career Lanciani collected a vast archive of his own
                  notes and manuscripts, as well as works by others including rare prints and
                  original drawings by artists and architects stretching back to the sixteenth
                  century. After his death in 1929, his entire library was purchased by the Istituto
                  Nazionale di Archeologia e Storia dell’Arte (INASA), on the recommendation of the
                  Director Corrado Ricci (1858-1934).</p>
                <p>To quote the librarian at the time of the accession, the Lanciani collection
                  "enriched the Roman topography section by almost 3,000 volumes and printed
                  brochures; [and by] several folders containing valuable notes for the continuation
                  of the history of the excavations of Rome and Lazio, that the death of the
                  illustrious archaeologist left interrupted, as well as about 15,000 prints and
                  loose drawings, and some books of drawings and sketches in pen and pencil by
                  artists such as Giani, Rossini and Caracciolo.” Lanciani considered this corpus
                  his personal collection, unlike one of similar importance that he donated to the
                  Vatican Library in 1925. Fittingly, the room that hosts the INASA collection is
                  called the “Sala Lanciani” and is now located on the fourth floor of the
                  Biblioteca di Archeologia and Storia dell’Arte (BIASA) in the historic Palazzo
                  Venezia in Rome.</p></quote>
            </note>
          </notesStmt>
        </biblFull>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Artists in Paris</title>
            <title type="sub">Mapping the 18<hi rend="superscript">th</hi>-Century Art World</title>
            <principal>
              <persName>
                <forename>Anna</forename>
                <surname>Williams</surname>
              </persName>
            </principal>
            <principal>
              <persName>
                <forename>Chris</forename>
                <surname>Sparks</surname>
              </persName>
            </principal>
            <funder>The Leverhulme Trust</funder>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Queen Mary University of London</publisher>
            <date from="2013" to="2018">2015-2018</date>
            <idno>https://www.artistsinparis.org</idno>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Fashion History Timeline</title>
            <funder>Samuel H. Kress Foundation</funder>
            <principal>
              <persName>
                <forename>Justine</forename>
                <surname>De Young</surname>
              </persName>
            </principal>
            <principal>
              <persName>
                <forename>Lourdes M.</forename>
                <surname>Font</surname>
              </persName>
            </principal>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Fashion Institute of Technology, State University of New York</publisher>
            <date from="2015">2015</date>
            <idno>https://fashionhistory.fitnyc.edu</idno>
          </publicationStmt>
          <notesStmt>
            <note>
              <p>The Fashion History Timeline is a project by FIT’s History of Art Department. The
                Timeline offers scholarly contributions to the public knowledge of the history of
                fashion and design. Consistent with this mission, the Timeline’s written commentary,
                research, and analysis provided by FIT students, faculty, and other members of the
                community is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike
                4.0 International License. Unless specifically noted, images used in the Timeline
                are not subject to this Creative Commons License applied to the written work from
                the Timeline. While every attempt at accuracy has been made, the Timeline is a work
                in progress. If you have suggestions or corrections, please contact us.</p>
            </note>
          </notesStmt>
        </biblFull>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Style Revolution, 1797-1804</title>
            <title type="sub">Le Journal des dames et des modes</title>
            <principal>
              <forename>Anne</forename>
              <surname>Higonnet</surname>
            </principal>
            <principal>
              <forename>Alex</forename>
              <surname>Gil</surname>
            </principal>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Columbia University Libraries</publisher>
            <date when="2019">2019</date>
          </publicationStmt>
          <notesStmt>
            <note>
              <p>This project is dedicated to the world’s most original and influential style
                magazine, the Journal des dames et des modes. The French Revolution of 1789 promised
                that all people could reinvent themselves. Between 1797 and 1804, after the
                political crisis of the first revolutionary years subsided, and before Napoleon
                demanded that women’s clothing become more conservative, the Journal des dames et
                des modes offered Europeans a startlingly new way to dress. It rejected the rules,
                shapes, and materials that had signaled static social rank in favor of mobile
                self-expression through consumer choice. This dramatic experiment in individualism
                freed men to dress as they have ever since, and for a brief time liberated women
                too.</p>
              <p>Here you will find, online for the first time, all the Journal des dames et des
                modes plates from the magazine’s most surprising years, 1797-1804, together with
                their transcribed and translated captions. The digital images were made from an
                extremely rare, complete set of the engravings, in exceptionally good condition,
                belonging to the Morgan Library and Museum—call numbers PML 5687, PML 5688, PML
                5689. Work on the vocabulary, text descriptions, locations, patterns, and historical
                context of the plates was begun by a faculty-student team based at Columbia
                University, and is ongoing.</p>
            </note>
          </notesStmt>
        </biblFull>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Mapping Art Markets in Europe, 1500-1800</title>
            <principal>
              <persName>
                <forename>Sophie</forename>
                <surname>Raux</surname>
              </persName>
            </principal>
            <funder>Agence nationale de recherche (France)</funder>
            <funder>Partner University Fund de la Face Foundation (Washington DC)</funder>
            <funder>FEDER</funder>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Université de Lille</publisher>
            <date from="2008" to="2015">2008-2015</date>
            <idno>http://www.artmarkets.eu</idno>
          </publicationStmt>
          <notesStmt>
            <note xml:lang="fr">
              <p>Quels étaient les grands centres du marché de l’art en Europe au 18<hi
                  rend="superscript">e</hi> siècle ? Qui en étaient les acteurs ? Dans quels réseaux
                professionnels et familiaux ces derniers s’inscrivaient-ils ? Où étaient situés les
                marchands de tableaux à Paris au siècle des Lumières ? A quoi ressemblait l’activité
                du marchande du Pont Notre Dame et la boutique de son plus célèbre occupant,
                François-Edmé Gersaint ?</p>
              <p>La base de données et les applications de visualisation proposées ici visent à
                restituer sous une forme inédite les résultats d’une équipe de chercheurs qui se
                sont penchés – entre autres – sur ces questions, dans le cadre du projet Art Markets
                in Europe. Emergence, Development, Networks, 1500-1800, soutenu par l’ANR.</p>
            </note>
          </notesStmt>
        </biblFull>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>The Royal Academy Summer Exhibition: A Chronicle, 1769-2018</title>
            <principal>
              <persName>
                <forename>Mark</forename>
                <surname>Hallett</surname>
              </persName>
            </principal>
            <principal>
              <forename>Sarah Victoria</forename>
              <surname>Turner</surname>
            </principal>
            <principal>
              <forename>Jessica</forename>
              <surname>Feather</surname>
            </principal>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Paul Mellon Centre for Studies in British Art</publisher>
            <pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
            <date when="2018">2018</date>
            <idno>https://chronicle250.com</idno>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Picturing Places</title>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>British Library</publisher>
            <date from="2013" to="2017">2013-2017</date>
            <idno>https://www.bl.uk/picturing-places</idno>
          </publicationStmt>
          <notesStmt>
            <note>
              <p>Picturing Places is a free educational resource providing unprecedented access to
                the British Library’s unrivalled holdings of topographical materials. The site
                highlights a selection of important items from our vast and varied collections,
                including prints, drawings, paintings, books, maps, letters, notes and ephemera.
                Users can examine high-resolution digitised images and read articles by emerging and
                established scholars exploring the history, context and significance of these
                images.</p>
              <p>Picturing Places demonstrates that topography involves far more than
                straightforward ‘pictorial evidence’ of what a place looked like in the past. We
                showcase some of the Library’s most treasured topographical materials, including
                Tudor views collected by Robert Cotton and maps and views owned by George III. But
                much of this material remains uncharted, and is being brought to wider attention for
                the first time. The first phase of Picturing Places features over 500 collection
                items, most never published before, and over 100 articles providing fresh
                perspectives and new ideas.</p>
            </note>
          </notesStmt>
        </biblFull>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>What Jane Saw</title>
            <principal>
              <forename>Janine</forename>
              <surname>Barchas</surname>
            </principal>
            <funder>Liberal Arts Instructional Technology Services (LAITS) at the University of
              Texas at Austin</funder>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Department of English, The University of Texas at Austin</publisher>
            <date from="2011" to="2015">2011-2015</date>
            <idno>http://whatjanesaw.org</idno>
          </publicationStmt>
          <notesStmt>
            <note>
              <p>This website (www.whatjanesaw.org) offers digital reconstructions of two museum
                blockbusters attended by Jane Austen: the Boydell Shakespeare Gallery in 1796 and
                the Sir Joshua Reynolds retrospective in 1813. The initial phase of “What Jane Saw”
                launched on 24 May 2013, or 200 years to the day that the Austens attended the
                Reynolds show. The second phase of the website launched in 2015, on 16 December,
                Austen's birthday. If you would like to “hear” Professor Barchas talk about this
                project, the Folger Shakespeare Library hosts a 30-min interview with her in the
                form of a podcast called Recreating the Boydell Gallery.</p>
            </note>
          </notesStmt>
        </biblFull>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>ARIES - ARt Image Exploration Space</title>
            <title type="sub">An interactive image manipulation system that enables the exploration
              and organization of fine digital art</title>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Frick</publisher>
            <date when="2018">2018</date>
            <idno>https://artimageexplorationspace.com/</idno>
          </publicationStmt>
          <notesStmt>
            <note>
              <p>Art historians have traditionally used physical light boxes to prepare exhibits or
                curate collections. On a light box, they can place slides or printed images, move
                the images around at will, group them as desired, and visually compare them. The
                transition to digital images has rendered this workflow obsolete. Now, art
                historians lack well-designed, unified interactive software tools that effectively
                support the operations they perform with physical light boxes.</p>
              <p>To address this problem, we designed ARIES - ARt Image Exploration Space, an
                interactive image manipulation system that enables the exploration and organization
                of fine digital art. The system allows images to be compared in multiple ways,
                offering dynamic overlays analogous to a physical light box, and supporting advanced
                image comparisons and feature-matching functions, available through computational
                image processing.</p>
              <p>ARIES: Enabling Visual Exploration and Organization of Art Image Collections
                Lhaylla Crissaff, Louisa Ruby, Samantha Deutch, Luke DuBois, Jean-Daniel Fekete,
                Juliana Freire and Cláudio T. Silva IEEE Computer Graphics and Applications, 38 (1),
                2018, 91-108.</p>
              <p>The team includes:<list>
                  <item>Lhaylla Crissaff (Universidade Federal Fluminense, Brazil)</item>
                  <item>João Lucas Rullf (New York University, USA)</item>
                  <item>Marcos Lage (Universidade Federal Fluminense, Brazil)</item>
                  <item>Louisa Wood Ruby (The Frick Collection, USA)</item>
                  <item>Samantha Deutch (The Frick Collection, USA)</item>
                  <item>Juliana Freire (New York University, USA)</item>
                  <item>Cláudio Silva (New York University, USA)</item>
                </list>
              </p>
            </note>
          </notesStmt>
        </biblFull>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Atlas des techniques de construction romaine</title>
            <funder>TransferS</funder>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Laboratoire AOROC (UMR 8546)</publisher>
            <date from="2012" to="2021">2012-2021</date>
            <idno>https://acor.huma-num.fr</idno>
          </publicationStmt>
          <notesStmt>
            <note>
              <p>Initié en 2012, le programme ACoR a pour objectif de développer un atlas des
                techniques de la construction romaine, sur un large champ géographique et
                chronologique. Il s'est concrétisé dans la réalisation d'une base de données,
                consultable sur ce site web, qui établit un corpus de techniques, identifiées,
                classées et localisées dans un territoire, un site et un édifice.</p>
              <p>À l'échelle de l'édifice, la caractérisation morphologique et technique des
                éléments de construction obéit à la logique des étapes d'un chantier, en distinguant
                les différentes interventions de construction : préparation du terrain, fondations,
                élévations, ouvertures, couvrements et couvertures, sols, structures de service et
                arcs (ces derniers pouvant être étudiés de façon autonome, ou en association avec
                une autre intervention). S'y ajoute une analyse spécifique des traces de chantier,
                communes à la plupart des interventions.</p>
            </note>
            <note>
              <p>Mise en ligne en 2021</p>
            </note>
          </notesStmt>
        </biblFull>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Open Art Data</title>
            <title type="sub">Linking Databases To Detect Looted Art</title>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher/>
            <date/>
            <idno>https://www.openartdata.org</idno>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>BlakeTint</title>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Yale DHLab</publisher>
            <date>2019-2020</date>
            <idno>https://dhlab.yale.edu/projects/blaketint/</idno>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title/>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>The Provenance Lab</publisher>
            <date when="2022">2022</date>
            <idno>https://whatisapainting.com</idno>
          </publicationStmt>
          <noteStmt>
            <note><p>The different definitions of 'painting' were retrieved from US museums
                classifications in the context of the project Modern Migrants: Paintings from Europe
                in US Museums of The Provenance Lab at Leuphana University.</p></note>
          </noteStmt>
        </biblFull>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Archival-city</title>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher/>
            <date from="2022">depuis 2022</date>
            <idno>https://archivalcity.hypotheses.org</idno>
          </publicationStmt>
          <noteStmt>
            <note><p>ARCHIVAL-CITY aims to propose new ways of accessing, viewing and using the city
                archives. Therefore, it is slated to become a key resource for better understanding
                and exploiting urban archives, and also to imagine, debate and plan the city of the
                future by incorporating robust data from the past. It will serve as the bridge and
                communication link that was missing between those who are interested in the city’s
                past and those building its future. Used not only by researchers, historians and
                archivists, but also by local government, policy-makers and urban operators, as well
                as citizens eager to take part in their urban environment.</p></note>
          </noteStmt>
        </biblFull>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Vespera</title>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher/>
            <date from="2013">depuis 2013</date>
            <idno>https://verspera.hypotheses.org</idno>
          </publicationStmt>
          <noteStmt>
            <note><p>Le projet de recherche VERSPERA, numérisation et modélisation des plans de
                Versailles sous l’Ancien Régime, vise à rendre accessibles à tous les plans du
                domaine de Versailles sous l’Ancien Régime et à en restituer certains espaces grâce
                à la numérisation et à la modélisation 3D.</p></note>
          </noteStmt>
        </biblFull>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Paris Time-machine</title>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher/>
            <date from="2019">depuis </date>
            <idno>https://paris-timemachine.huma-num.fr</idno>
          </publicationStmt>
          <noteStmt>
            <note><p/></note>
          </noteStmt>
        </biblFull>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Le plan de Rome</title>
            <title type="sub">Restituer la Rome antique</title>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher/>
            <date/>
            <idno>https://rome.unicaen.fr</idno>
          </publicationStmt>
          <noteStmt>
            <note><p>Le projet « Plan de Rome » est l’un des trois axes de l’ERLIS (Équipe de
                Recherche sur les Littératures, les Imaginaires et les Sociétés - EA 4254).
                L’objectif est de rendre toujours plus accessibles les sources anciennes à de larges
                publics en utilisant les technologies multimédias.</p></note>
          </noteStmt>
        </biblFull>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Digital Augustan Rome</title>
            <principal>
              <persName>
                <forename>David</forename>
                <surname>Gilman Romano</surname>
              </persName>
            </principal>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>The University of Arizona</publisher>
            <date/>
            <idno>https://www.digitalaugustanrome.org</idno>
          </publicationStmt>
          <noteStmt>
            <note><p/></note>
          </noteStmt>
        </biblFull>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Rennes et l’incendie de 1720</title>
            <principal>
              <persName>
                <forename>Laurent</forename>
                <surname>Gonthier</surname>
              </persName>
            </principal>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <idno>https://www.laurentgontier.com/Rennes_Incendie/</idno>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Lyon en 1700</title>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <idno>https://lyonen1700.fr</idno>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Imagine Rio</title>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <idno>https://www.imaginerio.org</idno>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Base de données du programme CIRCE</title>
            <title>Constructions, Interprétations et Représentations Cultuelles de l’Espace dans les
              sociétés anciennes</title>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <idno>https://circe-antique.huma-num.fr</idno>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
        <!-- https://hiddenflorence.org/about/ -->
        <!-- http://drc.usask.ca/projects/archbook/ -->
        <!--https://lkilroyewbank.org/tag/digital-art-history/-->
        <!-- http://arthistorians.info/about -->
        <!-- Dictionnaire critique des historiens de l’art actifs en France de la Révolution à la Première Guerre mondiale. Philippe Sénéchal et Claire Barbillon (dir.) https://www.inha.fr/fr/ressources/publications/publications-numeriques/dictionnaire-critique-des-historiens-de-l-art.html
             -->
        <!-- https://projectcornelia.be -->
        <!-- https://gist.github.com/antoinecourtin/2a5c833d7f5c1baf093e8f29b640847d -->
      </listBibl>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
